Register of the Valentine F. Morozoff papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Valentine F. Morozoff papers
1901-1996
2014C18
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes (3.5 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, financial records, personal documents, and photographs, relating to the Russian community in Japan. Includes papers of other Russians resident in Japan.
Morozoff, Valentine F.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2014.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Valentine Fedorovich Morozoff was a Russian émigré in Japan and president of the Russian Emigrants Society in Kobe, Japan. His important contribution to the Russian refugee colony was to clarify their legal status in Japan as stateless citizens under Japanese protection. Morozoff was also a successful businessman who became famous promoting chocolates, candies, and other Western style confections as part of Japan's new urban culture in the 1950s.
Scope and Contents of Collection
The papers of Valentine Morozoff document his activities as head of the Russian Emigrants Society in Japan, and include correspondence, financial records, meeting minutes, and other documents of the organization. The collection also includes letters of Dmitrii Abrikossow (Abrikosov), the last chargé d'affaires of the Russian Embassy in Tokyo. Also included are several photographs of Alexandra Tolstoy, daughter of Leo Tolstoy, and a set of photographs belonging to Pavel Vaskevich, the former Russian consul in Kobe. The collection also contains Morozoff's personal papers and photographs, relating to the Russian community in Japan. The materials are organized in two series: Individuals and Organizations file and Oversize materials, and arranged by subject or physical form in alphabetical order.
Russia--Emigration and immigration.; Russians--Japan.
- Individuals and Organizations file, 1901-1996
  - Abrikossow (Abrikosov), Dmitrii Ivanovich, letters to V. Morozoff, 1947-1951 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Balasheff, Iurii Mikhailovich, reference letters, 1949-1956 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Bobroff, Alexsander, priest, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Bratukhina, Natalia Vasilievna, correspondence, hospital's certificate, and personal property inventory, 1948-1951 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Cheremshanskii, Georgii (Iurii) Appolonovich, immigration papers, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Gordienko, Mikhail, priest, circa 1950 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Grigorieff, Arkadii Grigorievich, 1910-1965
    - Correspondence, 1948-1965 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Family photo album, 1910-1950 (Box 4)
  - Gusev, Varlam, autobiographical sketch and immigration papers, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - International Committee of Kobe and Osaka, 1955-1968
    - History, rules and bylaws, brochure, 1955 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - Meeting minutes, 1956-1968 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - Correspondence, 1956-1964 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Financial statements and contribution receipts, 1956-1967 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Kano, Kiroku, notes and photographs, 1940-1990 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Kazachkoff, Nikolai, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Kent, Nikolai, photographs, immigration and employment documents, 1922-1949 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Koch, Waldemar, reference letters, 1955 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Krasilnikoff, A., correspondence and immigration papers, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Krynskaia (Krynska), Ol'ga Evgenievna file, 1901-1966
    - Passport, 1923 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Employment papers, 1945-1952 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Correspondence, 1918-1966 (Box-folder 1: 20-23)
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes letter from D. Abrikossow, 1948
    - Notebooks, 1945-1961 (Box-folder 1: 24)
    - Photographs of family and friends, 1901-1965 (Box-folder 1: 25-26, 2: 1)
  - Malinin, Evgenii Dmitrtievich family papers, 1910-1996
    - Personal documents, 1910-1996 (Box-folder 2: 2-4)
    - Career file, 1940-1966 (Box-folder 2: 5-6)
      Includes photographs.
    - Correspondence, 1938-1996 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Notebooks, circa 1950 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Statements, financial records, and gift certificate, 1956-1996 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - Photographs, 1910-1996 (Box-folder 2: 10-13)
  - Meyeris (Meieris), Nadezhda D., will, 1964 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Russian Emigrants Society, Kobe, 1934-1990
    - History, statutes, and photographs, 1934-1990 (Box-folder 2: 15)
    - Membership, 1934-1964 (Box-folder 2: 16-17)
    - Financial records, 1941-1947 (Box-folder 2: 18-19)
    - Meeting minutes, 1946-1954 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Russian Orthodox Church in Kobe, 1939-1981
    - Photographs depicting church events and Russian cemetery services, 1939-1962 (Box-folder 3: 1-6)
    - Church construction file, correspondence, drawings, and financial records, 1947-1952 (Box-folder 3: 7-12)
    - Clippings, postcards, and other printed matter, 1950-1981 (Box-folder 3: 13-15)
  - Shevchenko, David, 1949-1953
    - Personal papers, 1949-1951 (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1953 (Box-folder 3: 17)
    - Material relating to his relocation from the Philippines to Japan, 1950-1953 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Tarasenko, A. D. family, correspondence, immigration application, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Tolstoy, Alexandra L'vovna, letter to Valentine Morozoff and photographs depicting her visit to Kobe, 1930-1941 (Box-folder 3: 20)
    Includes undated photograph of her with Lev Tolstoy, inscribed to Valentine Morozoff in 1931.
  - World Council of Churches, Service to refugees, Tokyo office, 1953-1958 (Box-folder 3: 21-22)
    Includes correspondence, reference letters, and other materials relating to the status of Russian refugees.
- Oversize materials, 1905-1950
  - Grigorieff family photo album, 1910-1950 (Box 4)
  - Pavel Vaskevich photo album, 1905-1953 (Box 6)
  - Photograph of the Pre-revolutionary Russian Embassy staff members in Tokyo, including D.M. Abrikossow (Abrikosov), circa 1915 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Photograph of the Russo-Japanese Commission for settling of the boundary in Sakhalin after the end of the war, circa 1905 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Plans and drawings of Valentine Morozoff and Pavel Vaskevich residences, Dairen, Japan, 1930 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)